<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://caliope.vub.ac.be/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://caliope.vub.ac.be/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-18T14:14:14+00:00</updated><id>https://caliope.vub.ac.be/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CALIOPE</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Who Am I?</title><link href="https://caliope.vub.ac.be/blog/2024/who-am-i/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Am I?"/><published>2024-05-16T11:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-16T11:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://caliope.vub.ac.be/blog/2024/who-am-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://caliope.vub.ac.be/blog/2024/who-am-i/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s about time I introduced myself. It’s not nice visiting someone’s (virtual) home without them even introducing themselves to the guests. Sure, you can find some info about me in the <a href="/people/">people</a> page, but those are just boring academic bio info that nobody really cares about. So who am I really?</p> <p>I’m Filippo Carnovalini, a researcher from Italy who really likes music, and likes computers. I tried to make my life and my job about those things, and I kind of managed to do just that: I have been researching computer science applied to sound and music for about six years now. Mostly, I have worked on algorithms and software for the goal of automatically composing music. CALIOPE, my current project, also does that, but with a spin: we want to generate exercises, rather than any kind of music. Well, musical exercises (like the boring scales you have to play to get faster with your hands, or even those complicated <em>études</em> by the great composers) are music pieces, but they are special. Rather than being composed only to be pleasant or interesting to listen to, they are made to make you a better player by mastering them. So, a whole new set of challenges.</p> <p>But I don’t want to get sidetracked with CALIOPE, we were talking about myself! Let’s try and say something else that is not really evident from my academic bio, without giving away the responses to any security questions for any account I have. I have a wife and daughter, who live with me in Brussels. I play the mandolin (and sometimes the guitar and piano) and like singing in choirs. As a hobby I like doing origami, and I like platformer video games, especially those with Italian plumbers in them. What else? I could go on, but if you want to know me better you probably should come and meet me at the campus of Vrije Universiteit Brussel, where I now work developing CALIOPE. I’ll be happy to offer you a coffee! Otherwise, keep following this blog (and my social accounts) and you may get to know a bit more about myself and my job.</p> <p>Ad maiora! <br/><span class="blog-signature">- Filippo Carnovalini</span></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="announcements,"/><category term="people"/><category term="research,"/><category term="life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Myself]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello World!</title><link href="https://caliope.vub.ac.be/blog/2024/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World!"/><published>2024-04-10T11:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-10T11:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://caliope.vub.ac.be/blog/2024/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://caliope.vub.ac.be/blog/2024/hello-world/"><![CDATA[<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Hello World!</code></p> <p>It’s always hard to choose the starting words for something you write, be it a new book, a website, or a blog. Unless you are a computer scientist, in which case you will probably start with the usual, “Hello World!”.</p> <p>And I really want to say hello to the whole world, as we launch the website for Project CALIOPE. Sure, it’s a bit empty right now, but it’s good to have a little place on the internet to call a home for the project. And I’ll try to keep this home as cozy and tidy as possible: by posting frequent updates here on the blog, by notifying every new publication and milestone, and by making sure that I always check if anyone interacts with the site (by the way, feel free to comment below!)</p> <p>Want to know more about CALIOPE? You could start by giving a look at the <a href="/">homepage</a>, or you could even read <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/370238322_Interactive_Generation_of_Musical_Corpora_for_Piano_Education_Opportunities_and_Open_Challenges">the paper</a> we wrote about the project before it even began (we like to always be one step ahead!), but in a nutshell here is what we are trying to do: we want to create a system that can create exercises to learn the piano that are personalized to each teacher and student that use it. Your own little exercise, created just for you, to make sure that you learn what your teacher wants you to learn this week. Artificial Intelligence is obviously going to play a role in here: understanding what the teacher wants you to learn, and then creating the exercise based on your proficiency level.</p> <p>It’s not going to be easy! But I really hope to be able to help shape a future in which music education embraces computing technologies, while keeping the (human) student-teacher interaction and at the heart of it.</p> <p>Ad maiora! <br/><span class="blog-signature">- Filippo Carnovalini</span></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="announcements,"/><category term="milestones"/><category term="research,"/><category term="website"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Website Launch]]></summary></entry></feed>